Finding aid for the Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers, 1883-1979
Bentley Historical Library
Harold Dunbar Corbusier papers
1883-1979 (scattered dates)
1900-1902
Bentley Historical Library
Corbusier, Harold Dunbar, 1873-1950.
2019013 Aa 2 UAl
2. 4 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
1 oversize folder
An orthopedic surgeon in the United States Army, author, inventor, and University of Michigan alumnus (B.S. and M.D. 1899). Corbusier served in the China Relief Expedition, the Philippines Campaign, the Mexican Border War, and World War I. The collection contains biographical information, correspondence, writings by Corbusier, collected articles and clippings, photographs and glass plate lantern slides, loose scrapbook materials, and a photo album. Materials document Corbusier's experiences during the China Relief Expedition, the Mexican Border War, the Philippines Campaign, and World War I. The collection also contains a small amount of materials focusing on his time as a student at the University of Michigan, as well as to his medical and military careers.
This collection is open without restriction.
Donated by Thomas S. Knox (donor no. 11890 ) in June 2018.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is arranged into 3 series: 1. Biographical, 1883-1950. 2. Correspondence, 1900-1979. 3. Visual Materials, 1898-1948.
Early Life and Education
Harold Dunbar Corbusier (1873-1950) was born in Yavapai County, Arizona Territory to Colonel William H. and Fannie Dunbar Corbusier. As a military family, the Corbusiers travelled between U.S. Army bases in Arizona, the Carolinas, Tennessee, Kansas, and the Midwest, including Fort Mackinac and Fort Wayne in Michigan (1882-1892). In 1893, Harold Corbusier entered the University of Michigan where he joined the Delta Upsilon Fraternity. He received both his Bachelor of Science and Medical degrees in 1899.
Military Career
After completing his education at the University of Michigan, Corbusier joined the Medical Department of the United States Army Reserve where he served in numerous military campaigns from 1900 to the end of World War I. From 1900 to 1905, Corbusier served as Acting Assistant Surgeon and in this capacity participated in the China Relief Expedition from 1900 to 1901 and in the Philippine Campaign from 1901 to 1902. Corbusier left active service in 1905, settling in Plainfield, NJ to raise a family with his wife Louise S. Corbusier, a Michigan native (1875-1964). The couple was married in 1930 and had two children, Frances (O'Brien) Corbusier and Nancy (Knox) Corbusier, born in 1913.
In 1909, Corbusier began his service with the National Guard of New Jersey. In 1911, he joined the Organized Reserves (Army). In 1916, Corbusier began his service with the New Jersey Guard on the Mexican Border. Here he organized and commanded the Guard's first medical units, also known as the "Sanitary Train." From 1917 to 1919, Corbusier served as a major in the United States Army Medical Corps.
Corbusier was placed in a number of leadership positions during and immediately after World War I, specifically between 1916 and 1919. He organized the Division of Orthopedic Surgery with the Surgeon General's Office (S.G.O.) subsequently serving as the Chief of Orthopedic Surgery. He also organized the first Reconstruction Company in the U.S. for soldiers with physical challenges. This system was later adopted by the War Department for Development Battalions. Corbusier served as Chief of the Orthopedic Service and instructor at the Medical Officers' Training Camp in Fort Oglethorpe, GA and as Chief of the Orthopedic Section and training officer at Camp Meade, MD. Corbusier also served as the First Assistant to the Chief of the Orthopedic Service, and as Chief of the Reconstruction Section of General Hospital #3 in Colonia, NJ.
In 1920, Corbusier was promoted to Lieutenant Colonel of the Medical Section Officer's Reserve Corps. During this period, Corbusier was also appointed as U.S. Delegate to the International Congress of Arthritis. In 1922, he was appointed Chief Surgeon for the 12th Army Corps Reserve and circa 1931, he was promoted to Colonel in the Medical Corps (U.S. Army). Between 1933 and 1948, Corbusier was also appointed as a U.S. Delegate to several International Congresses and travelled to Madrid, Brussels, Bucharest, Lima, and Havana.
Medical Career
After leaving active military service in 1905 and moving to Plainfield, NJ, Corbusier opened a private orthopedic clinic in 1908. In 1911, he joined the hospital staff at Muhlenberg hospital in Plainfield where he organized the Department of Orthopedic Surgery and Physical Therapy. In 1913, he was appointed Junior Attending Surgeon in the Department of Surgery. That same year he was also appointed Clinical Assistant in the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital. In 1916, Corbusier was appointed instructor in the Orthopedic Surgery Department. In 1923, Corbusier was named Muhlenberg hospital's Senior Attending Surgeon in Orthopedics. In 1936, he was appointed as Muhlenberg's Resident Consulting Surgeon. In 1945, he served as a consultant to the hospital's Physiotherapy Department.
Inventions
Corbusier used his talents and knowledge of orthopedic medicine to pioneer the U.S. Army's system of reconstruction and devised a system of "Recruit Rehabilitation and Training in Development Battalions." The latter being a manpower salvage method adopted by the U.S. Army for all large military camps. He also used his talents to design a special Army shoe known as the "Doughboy," that was worn by soldiers during WWI to counteract "Foot Weakness." He also designed the guidon, the first distinguishing flag used by the U.S. Army's Medical Department.
Civilian Life and Activities
Corbusier's civilian life was heavily intermingled with his military life. He served as an orthopedic and physio-therapeutic consultant to the Bureau of Public Health Service and as a consultant in Orthopedic Surgery and Physiotherapy to the Rehabilitation Commission of the American Legion in New Jersey, New York, and Connecticut. He also lent his consultation services to the U.S. Senate Committee for the investigation of the Veteran's Bureau.
Corbusier served as the President of the Association of Military Surgeons, President of the Academy of Physical Medicine of the United States, Vice-Chair of the Veterans of Foreign Wars National Rehabilitation Committee, Vice President of the American College of Physiotherapy, and Board member of the National Society for Crippled Children and Adults. He lent his services to the American Red Cross, the Association of the Medical Reserve Corps, the College of International Surgeons, numerous Military Orders, and the University of Michigan Alumni Club. Corbusier also served as an honorary member of the Mexican Association of Military Surgeons and the Russian Veterans' Association.
Harold Dunbar Corbusier passed away on August 31, 1950, leaving behind a long and distinguished career as a retired Colonel, military surgeon, and civic leader. Louise S. Corbusier died on September 3, 1964.
The papers of Harold Dunbar Corbusier include a range of materials focusing on his medical and military career with the United States Army Medical Corps and the Medical Department of the U.S. Army Reserves between 1900 and ca. 1945.
The Biographical series included his biography, a diary reflecting on his childhood experiences at Fort Mackinac in Michigan, a typed manuscript highlighting his experiences during the Boxer Rebellion in China. Also included here are his professional publications and collected articles, event programs and invitations.
The Correspondence series primarily includes letters to his then fiancé Louise Shepard, as well as letters from military and governmental departments, hospitals, and other military and medical associations. images The Visual Materials series includes glass plate slides and a photo album with images of Chinese landmarks and troops from the eight nations fighting against the Boxers. Also included are photographs mostly focusing on the China and Philippines campaigns, and loose scrapbook materials (mostly clippings) focusing on China and Asia in general.
China -- History -- Boxer Rebellion, 1899-1901.; China -- Description and travel.; China Relief Expedition -- (1900-1901); Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920.; Military life.; Military officers.; Philippines -- History -- Philippine American War, 1899-1902.; Physicians.; World War I, 1914-1918.; Diaries.; Lantern slides.; Negatives.; Photo albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Corbusier, Harold Dunbar, 1873-1950.; United States. Army. Medical Reserve Corps.; United States. War Department.; University of Michigan -- Students.
- Biographical, 1883-1950 (scattered dates); undated
  The Biographical series includes a typed biography, a diary reflecting on Corbusier's childhood experiences at Fort Mackinac, MI, a typed manuscript highlighting his experiences during the Boxer Rebellion, articles about Corbusier's medical, military, and civilian life, and his writings on the subject of orthopedics in military service published in The Soldier's Foot and The Conservation of Man Power for War.
  Also, collected materials from Corbusier's time at the University of Michigan (including a set of his handwritten class notes from Medical School, 1896-1897), special and general military orders, certificates pertaining to his medical, military, and civilian life endeavors, programs and invitations to international congresses and meetings. Collected materials also include a leather swatch from a "doughboy" boot.
  - Articles about Corbusier, 1917-1946 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Articles re: Military Campaigns, Circa 1900-1918 (with gaps); undated (Box 1)
    Newspaper clippings about Corbusier, and the Boxer Rebellion in China.
  - Biography, undated (Box 1)
  - Certificates, identification cards, 1900-1950 (scattered dates); undated
    - 1900-1949 (with gaps), undated (Box 1)
    - 1933-1950 (with gaps), undated; 1 oversize folder (Folder 1)
  - Collected Materials (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan, 1896-1949 (with gaps) (Box 1)
      (Includes photographs)
    - Miscellaneous, 1900-1936 (scattered dates); 1936; undated (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1883-1892 (Box 1)
  - Military Orders, 1898-1941 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Works authored by Corbusier, 1905-1943 (scattered dates); undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1900-1979 (scattered dates); undated
  Of particular note in the Correspondence series are photocopies of over 61 handwritten letters to Corbusier's then fiancé Louise S. Shepard dating between 1900 and 1905. These letters, which highlight Corbusier's military experiences, were written primarily during his time in China and in the Philippines.
  The series includes letters addressed to Corbusier from the military, from several medical associations, other governmental departments, and hospitals. In particular, materials include letters from the War Department regarding Corbusier's appointments and reappointments and letters from the Treasury Department's Bureau of Health Service regarding his appointment as an orthopedic and physio-therapeutic consultant. Also found here is correspondence from the Association of Military Surgeons of the United States regarding Corbusier's appointments as delegate to several international meetings on leprosy, pharmaceuticals, military medicine, and physiotherapy.
  The series also includes letters regarding Corbusier's nomination to Plainfield, NJ Board of Health, his appointment as Junior Attending Surgeon with the Muhlenberg Hospital, and his appointments with the New York Post-Graduate Medical School and Hospital. Other items to note include membership letters to numerous organizations including the College of International Surgeons, and the Veterans of Foreign Wars National Rehabilitation Committee.
  - To Corbusier, 1913-1950 (scattered dates); undated (Box 1)
  - To Louise Shepard, 1900-1905 (with gaps); 3 folders (Box 1)
  - To Louise Shepard (transcribed letters), 1902-1903; 1979; undated (Box 1)
    Transcribed versions of letters written by Corbusier to his then fiance Louise Shepard between 1900 and 1903. Also includes correspondence from 1979 between Nancy Knox (daughter) and the American Heritage Publishing Co. The latter are in regard to a proposed article about the United States involvement with the Boxer Uprising in China.
- Visual Materials, 1898-1948 (scattered dates); undated
  The Visual Materials series includes labeled glass plate slides pertaining to the Boxer Rebellion as well as numerous photographs of the military campaigns in China and Mexico, and military training camps. The series includes a photo album depicting locations in China, proofs and negatives with images relating to the China and Philippine campaigns, and loose scrapbook materials (mostly newspaper clippings) pertaining to China and Asia in general. The series also includes a number of photographs documenting Corbusier's civilian life.
  In addition, a cloth map of North Eastern China (1900) and several cyanotype images of Queen Victoria's international funeral procession.
  - Glass Plate Slides, undated
    - HDC China Slides, undated (Box 2)
      Contains slides 1-111.
    - China Slides Box I, undated (Box 2)
      Contains slides 113 - 161. Missing slide 112.
    - China Slides Box II, undated (Box 2)
      Contains slides 162 - 184. Includes an unnumbered slide titled "Pekin Indians."
    - Inventory list, undated (Box 1)
      Inventory list of slides as well as two cards (programs) regarding his presentation of the slides to the Historical Society of Plainfield and North Plainfield (New Jersey).
  - Map of North Eastern China, 1900 (Box 1)
    (Cloth map)
  - Photographs, 1900-1936 (scattered dates); undated
    - Military Campaigns - China and Mexico, 1900-1916 (scattered dates); undated (Box 1)
      Includes stereoscopic slides of Chinese Boxer soldiers, Chinese casualties, the Peiho River, guns from the H.M.S. "Terrible," and American and Japanese soldiers.
    - Photo album of China, 1900-1901 (Box 3)
    - Proofs and Negatives re: China and the Philippines, 1900; undated (Box 1)
    - Training Camps, 1915, 1921
      - Tobyhanna, PA, 1921; undated (Box 1)
      - Tobyhanna, PA and Fort Oglethorpe, GA, 1915; 1917; 1 oversize folder (Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook Materials, 1903-1918; undated; 8 folders (Box 1)